<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Londons remonstrance to the Parliament, in subscribing to the propositions of both houses, concerning money, plate, horse, horsemen, and armes to be lent for the maintenance of an army for the Kings peace, and the safety of the Parliament as it was concluded by the lord maior, court of aldermen, and common-councell-men of the citie of London in Guild-Hall ; and by the masters, wardens, &amp;c. of all companies in each severall hall : with the just summe and proportion of money and plate collected, and to be presented to the Parliament : received by Sir Iohn Wollaston Knight and alderman, Alderman Towse, Alderman Warner, and Alderman Andrewes / written by I. H. Gent.</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45364</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H47</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20641</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12679934</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12679934</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65620</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45364)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65620)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 252:E152, no 10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Londons remonstrance to the Parliament, in subscribing to the propositions of both houses, concerning money, plate, horse, horsemen, and armes to be lent for the maintenance of an army for the Kings peace, and the safety of the Parliament as it was concluded by the lord maior, court of aldermen, and common-councell-men of the citie of London in Guild-Hall ; and by the masters, wardens, &amp;c. of all companies in each severall hall : with the just summe and proportion of money and plate collected, and to be presented to the Parliament : received by Sir Iohn Wollaston Knight and alderman, Alderman Towse, Alderman Warner, and Alderman Andrewes / written by I. H. Gent.</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
                  <author>J. H., Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Harrison,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Iune 26, 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65620:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDONS</hi> REMONSTRANCE TO THE PARLIAMENT, In ſubſcribing to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of both HOUSES, Concerning Money, Plate, Horſe, Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Armes to be lent for the maintenance of an Army for the Kings Peace, and the ſafety of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>As it was concluded by the Lord Maior, Court of Aldermen, and Common-Councell-men of the Citie of LONDON, in <hi>Guild-Hall;</hi> and by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Wardens, &amp;c. of all Companies in each ſeverall Hall.</p>
            <p>With the juſt ſumme and proportion of Money and Plate collected, and to be preſented to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Received by Sir <hi>Iohn Wollaſton</hi> Knight and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Alderman <hi>Towſe,</hi> Alderman <hi>Warner,</hi> and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Andrewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by <hi>I. H.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>London printed for <hi>Iohn Harriſon. Iune</hi> 23. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:65620:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65620:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LONDONS</hi> REMONSTRANCE TO THE PARLIAMENT, In ſubſcribing to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of both HOUSES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince by too-apparent demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations it appeares, that the King (deluded, and ſeduced by the evill Counſels of a malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant party, whoſe Spirits are ill-affected to the publike peace of this Kingdome) intendeth to make warre againſt the Parliament, and that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the ſame intention, he hath already col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and levyed great forces both of Horſe and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65620:3"/> Foot, to maintain the former reſolution throughout the County of <hi>York,</hi> and a multitude of Papiſts, and other reſolute and ill-diſpoſed perſons in other Counties adjacent; all which doe apparently inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate his reſolution to make warre againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: They have therefore after a ſerious and deliberate conſideration thereof, propounded cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Propoſitions to the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> deſiring their aſſiſtance in a preſent ayde for the ſecurity of both Houſes; for otherwiſe the pernicious malice of ſuch deſperate perſons, imployed in ſo horrid, and unnaturall an Act, will be ready to commit all outrage and violence, which will conſequently tend to the diſſolution of this preſent governement, the violation of the Priviledges of Parliament, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our Religion, and all hopes in refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Church, to the perpetuall ruine of the Lawes, the liberty and propriety of the Subjects. Wherefore the Lords and Commons, conſidering how great an obligation doth lie upon them in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Conſcience, and Duty, according to the high truſt repoſed in them by the whole Kingdom, to uſe all poſſible meanes in ſuch caſes for the timely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of ſo great and irrecoverable evils, have thought it expedient to publiſh their ſence and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of theſe imminent dangers; thereby to excite and extimulate all well-affected perſons to contribute their reſpective aſſiſtance to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations neceſſary for the oppoſing and ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the trayterous attempts of thoſe malignant ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. The Citie of <hi>London</hi> ſeemed to ſympathize
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65620:3"/> exceedingly with theſe Propoſitions: and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament were not more ready to propound them, then they as ready to performe, and obey the ſame.</p>
            <p>Laſt Tueſday the Lord Maior, Court of Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Common-Councell-men, met at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> in diſtribution of their affections, and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations what ſhould be diſpenſed out of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Treaſurie. Every Company likewiſe did meet at their Halls, and there diſtributed every man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively; for men had better diſpenſe with their Money and Plate, conditionally to receive the ſame with intereſt, and have the publike faith of the whole Kingdome engaged for the ſecurity thereof, then being parſimonious and refractory, perhaps have that Money and Plate taken violently from them by inteſtine enemies: and let any man judge, Whether the prevention of ſuch impendent dangers be not more plauſible then the policy and diligence of a Remedie, when extremity ſhall drive a man to the laſt hopes: It is more eaſie to keepe out of dangers, then to get out of them. Wherefore it were more prudent for men (that can ſpare mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, without any detriment or prejudice to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) to diſpenſe with what money they can, for the conſervation of peace voluntarily, then when violent warre ſhall come ruſhing in upon us, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe then with compulſion; or elſe perhaps to be reduced to an eſtate not leſſe miſerable then ſlaviſh. But not to hold the Readers deſiring eye in any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſuſpenſe, I will delineate, and expreſſe the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular proportion of moneys gathered in <hi>London.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:65620:4"/> The Lord Maior, Court of Aldermen, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Councell-men, ſitting at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> made a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall determination of their intents, and have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſed fifty thouſand pounds, partly out of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Treaſury, and partly out of their owne purſes; and will maintaine fifty Horſe. Moſt of the twelve Companies have diſpenſed twenty thouſand pounds a piece; and of the other Companies, ten thouſand pounds is the leaſt that any have disbuſed: beſides an infinite number of Plate that is lent, of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne worth. Some Companies maintain three-ſcore Horſe, ſome forty, ſome thirty, but twenty is the leaſt that any Company maintaines, with as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Horſe men: for the preſervation of the publike peace and tranquility of the Kingdome, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall defence of the King, and both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. The affection of no man was meaſured by any limitation, but according to the proportion of his offer, he expreſſed his good will to this ſervice. But according to the appointment and direction of both Houſes of Parliament, the Money, Plate, Horſe, or Horſe-men were delivered to Sir <hi>Iohn Wollaſton,</hi> Knight and Alderman, Alderman <hi>Towſe,</hi> Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Warner,</hi> and Alderman <hi>Andrewes:</hi> for they were Ordered to be Treaſurers to receive all the Money and Plate, brought in for the purpoſes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. And the Acquittances of them, or of any two of them (as it was ordered by the Parliament) for the Receit of the ſame is a ſufficient ground for the Party ſo lending Money, or Plate, to demand the ſame againe with intereſt; and likewiſe conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65620:4"/> for the faſhion of the Plate. The totall ſumme of all the Moneys and Plate that the Citie hath brought in to the ſaid Aldermen, is ſuppoſed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to above ten hundred thouſand pounds: the Horſe and Horſe-men to the number of about eight hundred and fifty; but there are many more Horſe in preparation to bee ſent.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
